<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A students lamentation that hath sometime been in London an apprentice for the rebellious tumults lately in the citie hapning: for which fiue suffred death on Thursday the 24. of Iuly last.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B15986</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841738</idno>
  <idno type="VID">176907</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248569950</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 23401.5</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S106013</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99841738e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B15986)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176907)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 718:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A students lamentation that hath sometime been in London an apprentice for the rebellious tumults lately in the citie hapning: for which fiue suffred death on Thursday the 24. of Iuly last.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By E. Allde] for William Blackvvall, ..,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1595]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With woodcut title vignette.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: An admonition to all prentises.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 23401a on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴(-A1) B-C⁴(-C4).</note>
                  <note>Title page cropped at foot, with some loss of imprint (publication date from STC).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Apprentices --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176907:1"/>
            <p>A Students Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that hath sometime been in London an Apprentice, for the <hi>rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous tumults lately in the Citie hapning:</hi> for which fiue suffred death on Thursday the 24. of <hi>Iuly</hi> last.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Obedientia serui Corona.</hi>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a male figure being hanged from a gibbet or gallows, and a second male figure on a ladder with a noose being held over his head; nearby groups of soldiers and men on horseback, and a fire</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at London for William Blackvvall, and are to be sold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:176907:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176907:2"/>
            <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLE Reader, when <hi>Solon</hi> made lawes, he left out a punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente for Parricides, and being demaunded why he had omitted a penaltie for so haynous an offence, he had on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this to answer: It was vnnecessarye to name such a sinne, because he thought no childe so vnnaturall: or if there were, he vtterly disliked that either the name of so vile a person, or the nature of his crime, should to posteritie be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred. From whence, diuers wise Magist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates haue obserued, that sundrye capitall offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, haue had their names obscured with their deathes. But seeing this age (abounding in all iniquitie) affordeth more example of wilfull ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, than euer any other: I thinke it necessary all perswasions and examples should be vsed to perswade to good and deterre from euill. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:176907:3"/> haue I made bolde to imprinte this little Pamphlet, beeing a Students lamentation, that was borne, fostred, and hath sometime beene a Prentise in this Citie, which I am persvvaded in the zeale of his heart he vvrit, to vvinne all yong men from vvilfulnes to faithfull obedience, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly life, and gentle behauiour. To the vvell minded, he douteth not his good vvill vvilbe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable: the other that are rude and inconsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate, he lesse regardeth, though he would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linglye lay dovvne his life to see them liue as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seemerh honest seruants. His paines &amp; my expence are heere included: If it vvin any one to doe vvel our desire is satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine euer. W. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:176907:3"/>
            <head>A Students lamentation, that hath <hi>in London bene sometime an Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise:</hi> for the vnruly tumults, lately in that Citie hapning.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>H that my eyes were springes of teares, and my head a fountaine of water, that I might weepe sufficiently for the offences com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, by them to whome one parte of my deerest loue is conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated: I haue in my tytle show<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the estate I liue in, and not beene ashamed to manifest what I haue beene, that is, an Apprentise of London, that famous Citie, the mother Citie of this royall Kingdome.</p>
            <p>To which Citie <hi>&amp; patria &amp; parente,</hi> I am behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and therefore most of all to it &amp; the inhabitants therein account my selfe bound, being the first place wherin I breathed, and learnt the duties of a childe, a seruant and a subiect: Which duties, considering how some prentises of that Citie haue vtterly forgot, maketh me perforce to breake foorth into teares: and
<pb facs="tcp:176907:4"/> where I striued to keepesilence, my spirite with the Prophet <hi>Ieremies</hi> was vexed within me, and my speech brake foorth like a flame of fire. And albeit I haue no eloquence to disswade from sedition, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade to obedience, yet will I trye what loue, sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and pitie can doe, which if they could worke as easilye and earnestly as they be in me exceeding, I should not dout to make all honest minded people to detest, not only the man of sedition, but euery cause that giueth light thereto.</p>
            <p>But why talke I of the honest in this case, when not the Heathen led by nature, the Iewe trayned by the commaundements of the lawe, the Christian ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercised in the comfortes of the Gospell, the Turke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed by the confused Alcoron, but haue honored the magistrate with aldutious reuerence, imbracing concorde as chiefe maintainer of euery well guided Common-wealth. Alas how vnworthie is he to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the image of a man, that seeing the hurt that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth sedition, and will yet endeuour him selfe to disturbe a peaceable Estate? He that considereth how much blood must needs be shed, how many shall help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leslye be slaine, what store of houses spoyled, what multitudes of men vndone, how many wiues defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, virgins rauished in the fury of sedition: but wold detest the Author of it, were it his naturall sonne? He that bethinketh of the end of all rebellions, when af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bloody violence, the streets &amp; fieldes lye scattered here legs, there heads, these deadly wounded, those
<pb facs="tcp:176907:4"/> vtterly dead: is it possible that he can so cast off huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, that he had not rather dye himselfe, then liue to see so many miseries? Do wee punish a fellon with death, not spare a rauisher, a mansleaer or a murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, and shall we not more vehemently prosecute law against a sower of sedition, a beginner of insurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, a ringleader to rebellious actions? whenby his meanes all fellons, rauishers, manslears or murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, shall haue libertie to steale, defloure, kill, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, no man resisting, no lawe reproouing? But it may (by some) be here obiected, sedition and rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are vnfit tearmes to be vsed in the case I am now to handle: for the Prentises of London had no sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous purpose, no intention of open rebellion. Truely I perswade me, a headlong wilfulnes continued by custome of abused libertie, gaue first fyre to this vnad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uised flame: but he that shall dout, that a most treche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous resolution, and dangerous purpose followed, shall make question at a most apparant truthe. For was it not cleerely prooued by the confession of their owne mouthes, that they intended to enter Tower streete, rifle certaine houses, where powder, muniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and weapons were in greate aboundance? did they not scatter Libels, apoint a meeting place, there had they not many conferences? from thence made they not head to Tower hill, where (as likewise be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in More fieldes, by honest Prentses their intent being opened) they were preuented of entring Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er streete, and performing their purpose of entring to
<pb facs="tcp:176907:5"/> the store-houses of munition? Got not they first a pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, then a trumpetter? resisted not they the officers a long while with stones? contemnd they not her Maiesties proclamation, by which they were three times charged to auoyd: Haue not since been more Libels scattered, prouoking her Maiestie to iustice, when they should humblie haue sought mercie? O let me beseech all faithfull subiectes to amend these courses by the example of the offenders ouer sight, who indeed were not all Prentises, but <hi>Grant</hi> that needs would be the Captaine, was a very idle mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shift: of which too many frequent peopled places: Neither ought it to be concealed, but to all England made manifest, that albeit a number of careles boyes (set on by euill disposed persons) attempted these thinges: yet the better sorte of Prentises, yea and the greater sorte, neuer stird in these haynous acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but as faithfull subiectes in euery quarter of the Citie discouered the offenders: and before the seate of iudgement, those good Prentises gaue euidence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the euill, wherein they discharged that dutie, which both the lawe of God and custome of all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons commaundeth and commendeth.</p>
            <p>How full is the scripture of commaundement and example that subiectes should obay authority? Was not <hi>Miriam</hi> stroken with Leprosie for murmuring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Moses? Corah, Dathan,</hi> &amp; their companie swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed quicke for their rebellion? did not <hi>Absalom</hi> pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish in the prime of his yeares? <hi>Sheba</hi> in the greatest
<pb facs="tcp:176907:5"/> of his strength, for their rebellion. Did not <hi>Shimei</hi> fall in old age dishonorably euen for reuiling the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestrate when he was yong? Doth not Christ and his apostles warn vs to be subiect to the higher pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers euen for conscience sake knowing that the sword is not borne in vaine? yea whether it be to the King, or those in authority vnder him: and shall boies, shall seruants, that are subiected vnder meane subiectes presume against the higher powers, be law-makers that know not law, be institutors of orders, and will not themselues be ordered: No God forbid that euer that confusion should come among vs.</p>
            <p>To shew examples forraine what hurt hath come by sedition, and what misery hath faln the seditious, needes not greatly? seeing our owne Chronicles are full: yet for decorum sake I will induce som. <hi>Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem</hi> the beauty of the world besieged by the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> felt more misery within by ciuill sedition, than vexation without by the cōmon enemy, their store houses were fixed, famine followed, the mother eate her child: the seditious entred houses, where they found meate they beat them, where none they beate them, saying to the one they had and hid it, to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were worthy of stripes for that they gaue it not vnaskt. Lastly that famous City came to helplesse desolation, sedition beeing the onely meane of her destruction. Did not sedition ouerthrow <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, Corinth, Lacedaemon, Thaebes</hi> and made all <hi>Greece</hi> subiect to the <hi>Romaines?</hi> was not <hi>Rome</hi> it
<pb facs="tcp:176907:6"/> selfe euen ruyned, and the whole world pestred with the factions of <hi>Silla</hi> and <hi>Marius, Casar, Pompey</hi> and such like? In later yeares, hath not the greater part of Christendome, as <hi>Constantinople,</hi> all <hi>Greece,</hi> the middle earth Ilands, and sundry other Christian Kingdomes been brought to Turkish slauery, onely by sedition? Did not <hi>Cesar</hi> first conquer Englād fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered by sedition? did not <hi>Canutus</hi> enter England, ayded by sedition? O cruell sedition, O venemous hatred, O vnluckie debate, O pernitious dissention, O spiteful rancour, O blind and euer hurtfull enuie, O seldome well ending malice: why dost thou in one houre marre more than in an hundred yeres can be restored? What folly, what madnes is this, to make a hole in the ship thou saylest?</p>
            <p>For the seditious themselues: how miserably pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished <hi>Eleazar, Iehochanan</hi> and <hi>Schimeon</hi> in <hi>Ierusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem?</hi> In <hi>Rome</hi> howended <hi>Catiline?</hi> how <hi>Pompey</hi> and <hi>Casar</hi> after all their factions? In <hi>Greeces</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient gouerment, what end had <hi>Themistocles, Nici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, Alcibiades,</hi> and others? In <hi>Greeces</hi> latter gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, what end had the factious States against their Emperour <hi>Constantine</hi> the last? Haue not all these perished, being otherwise famous Captaines, Princely and Nobly borne, and shall vulgar peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, nay inconsiderate boyes haue any hope to pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in tumultuous riots? No assuredly, for as the great escape not, the baser cannot choose but perish. Of Iacke Straw, Will Waw, Wat Tiler, Tom
<pb facs="tcp:176907:6"/> Miller, Hob Carter and a number more such sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous inferiour ringleaders to seditions and conspira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies most notable, what hath been the end? Misery, destruction, and shame. All these at the beginning would be Reformers, &amp; wrongs forsooth they went about to right: but when they had got head, what wrong did they not count right? sought they not to roote out Learning? drew they not honest Citizens to death? slew they not noble Councellors? Put they not the royall person of the King oft times in feare and ieopardie? made they not euen this Citie Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don a shambles, a place of horror, yea, almost of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation? Is there anie in England, that hath not heard of Palme sunday field, Blacke Heath field, and manie other? how manie widowes made they? how manie fatherlesse children? Both these begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by such deformed Reformers. O hatefull ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, euen of folly it selfe to bee derided: when the scholler shall attempt to correct his master, the childe the father.</p>
            <p>But how euer I greeue on the one side at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suming folly of such witlesse Prentises, as haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended: I reioyce manie times more at the faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of those Prentises that reuealed their offence. For what greater proofe of their fidelitie could bee had, than in a case so dangerous as this was like to prooue, to deale so faithully in the disclosing thereof? What hope shall all good men haue of these young men (if Straungers should inuade) that haue not
<pb facs="tcp:176907:7"/> spared their owne companions, in a case of insurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Surely, by them hath London no little cause of ioy, That her Maiestie and the Nobilitie are as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured, there are in her such Prentises, as preferre no familiaritie before faithfull dutie, accounting those frends foes, that seeke to disturbe Englands peace. Bee ioyfull, you resolute and well gouerned young men, whom her Maiestie taketh for faithfull Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects and dutifull Prentices: and hath indeede so found you. Let them be sorrie that haue deserued sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. Bee you sorrie onely for this, that these offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders haue caused her Maiesty to striue with hir mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull nature, and commit them to Iustice.</p>
            <p>O consider yong men, how it greeueth her, and forget not what would haue befalne you, though you thinke little of such a mischiefe? There are in England hollow harted traitors that wayt such times as these, and would gladly set in foote to see your parents murdered, your sisters rauished, your owne throats cut, and think you heare England in her owne person, thus lamenting for <hi>Londons</hi> yong mens disobedience. Why doo yee deuide your selues within me? are yee not all mine? Shall the hand teare out the eye, the foote put the neck in ieopardy? you are my weapons, will yee fight against me? my sustentation, will yee famish me? part of my strength will yee striue to weaken mee. London is the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of my eye, the ancient honor of my signiory, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moused through all lands for plenty and peaceable
<pb facs="tcp:176907:7"/> gouernment: and will you seeke to ruyne her good report by wilfull stubbernesse? Hath my soueraigne mistresse, our careful Soueraigne, honored your Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie so often with her royall presence, delights she to be neare you euer? and haue you no delight but in disturbing her? Remember your owne mothers, how tender they were ouer you in your infancie, not suffering neighbours children nay not your owne brethren and sisters to abuse you: and thinke you her sacred Maiestie kind mother of all true English children, taketh your violence in good part? No, I assure ye? your wilfull offending and obstinate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in guilt, hath more greeued her Princely heart, than if an hoast of enemies had bent their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to inuade my bosome. For her Excellencie may say (which I too certainly feele): No meruayle if Spaine (the common scourge of all Christendome) attempt to disturbe our peacefull gouernment, when our owne subiects (meanly conditioned, of low and inferiour calling) will presume to assaile our Presi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, resist their Gouernours, kindle a sedition in the heart of our Realme, euen in London: which we tender as the apple of our eye.</p>
            <p>Thus might England (could shee speake) vtter her greefe. Be then ashamed you neglectfulll yong men, I am ashamed to call you Prentises: for how can I call you by that name which you despise. For Prentises indeed are those, that bewrayed your pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctises: such, as being seruants know how to obay,
<pb facs="tcp:176907:8"/> that being masters they may be obeyed: for it is as great praise for a subiect to obay dutifully, as a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour to rule well. Bethinke your selues, you wylde youths, what feare through all England is spred for your faults. How manie doubtfull parents in Shyres farre off from London tremble to heare these euill newes, least their children should be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of this same tumultuous ryot: be resolute to doo well (if there be anie among you doubtfull) and bee not discouraged at the punishment of those that haue deseruedly suffered: but be rather confirmed in well dooing. For as sweete flowers prosper best when the Gardener hath cast foorth vnwholesome weedes, so shall you bee sent-pleasing Blossomes, when these corrupt ones are remooued from you. And remember here the law hath beene executed with all mercy and fauour: for those that were first punished, the shame was onely seene, the correction not felt. Those that had more capitally in case of treason offended, their correction was with all pity, their members not distributed on gates but buryed in their graues. O neuer ending pitty of our royall Soueraigne: how often hath she winked at great riots committed by the youth of this Citty, and now when their offence is proued rebellion by statute law, she hath pitty that she must punish, and in their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment her royall pittie more appeareth, O you that are already criminate: humble your hearts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the throne of heauen. Be ashamed that you
<pb facs="tcp:176907:8"/> haue moued so gracious a princesse to iust displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure: and you vntoucht that are stubberne hearted, learne to submit. For onely submition winneth mercy, wilfulnes hasteth iudgement. If any treche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous insinuater goe about to intice you to insurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: if any idle headed libeller scatter papers amongst you, winne neuer dying praise by detecting them, for vndoubtedly you shall to God doo acceptable ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, to her maiestie the duties of faithfull subiects, of this Citty in your yong daies bee accounted preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and you shall make all trechors afraide to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueale their seditious practises. As for you that are guilty, haue mercy on your owne soules by confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing your sinnes with heart sorrow, and make satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction by aduising other, least they fall into like ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity. Weep for your offences, and we will weepe with you: pray, and we will pray with you: that the example and sorrow of you and your other fellows, may terrifie: and intreate all subiects and seruants, that they obaye her Maiesties Proclamations in their most headlong time of folly: for he that contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth authoritie, contemneth the ordinance of God: which who euer disobeyeth, hasteneth to himselfe heauie and sodaine iudgement. Which God, though sometime in his righteous vengeance, he send iust warre to punish vniust people: yet neuer are sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects counted Gods instruments that lift their hands against their Superiours, as I haue alreadie proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: For if <hi>Ioseph</hi> to <hi>Pharaoh, Dauid</hi> to persecuting
<pb facs="tcp:176907:9"/>
               <hi>Saul, Daniel</hi> to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> our Sauiour to <hi>Tiberius Nero, Paul</hi> and the Apostles to vniust <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> and the Romane Presidents, the Fathers of the Primitiue Church to tyrannous Tormentors, all whose examples Christians ought to follow. How vnworthie is he of a Christians name, nay of a mans name, that against his naturall Souereigne, a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull a peace maintaining Princesse will offer to lift his hand? Looke into Fraunce, long troubled with ciuill warres: into the Low Countries, whose earth hath manie yeares been drunke with blood. It was not thought at the beginning, this miserie would haue been. But now they are so exercised to dissenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that they haue no yere of rest, but Warre like a Lion rageth, men of one Nation either deuouring o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And if in Fraunce it is no small obseruaunce, that if their children on eeuenings meete, casting themselues into companies and fight, it is held with them for anominous presage of greater insuing mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe. What shall be thought in London, when not children in strength, though verie babes in wit, shall meete, conspire, complot against reuerent Magistra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. Well, Mercie hath taken Iustice by the hand, and they that compassion cannot intreate, compulsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will inforce. Remember, remember your selues, you yong men of London: is not libertie better than imprisonment: the fauour of her Maiestie more pleasing, than her heauie displeasure? Remember all the insolent follies she hath graciously forgiuen the
<pb facs="tcp:176907:9"/> Prentises of this Citie: remember your Parents, how glad they would bee of your wel dooing, how sorrowfull to heare of your owne sought for destruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And lastly bethinke ye of what I first vrgde: how manie sorrowes follow sedition, as murder, massacring, rape, robberie, all outrage: the father wounding the sonne sprung from his owne seede, the sonne murdring the father cause of his first bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. O imbrace peace, you that haue been borne in peace: and crie to God for peace on earth, with that diuine Poet,</p>
            <q>Nulla salus bello, pacem te precimus omnes.</q>
            <p>Which God of his mercie soften the stubborne harts of all the wilfull, confirme the better sort in their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience: blesse <hi>England</hi> from outward, but especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally from inward Enemies: encrease his Church, preserue our Souereigne (vnder God) chiefe cause of our peace and prosperitie: and hasten their destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that wish the contrary.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:176907:10"/>
            <head>A breefe Admonition to those idle persons liuing about London, whose sloth makes them apt for any sinne: Beeing but certaine gathered notes from <hi>Grants</hi> example.</head>
            <p>YOU flumbring idle persons, whose life about this Citie is vayner than a dreame: whose dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes are very likely to be shameful and desperat: to you, to you (if you would heare) should be said, but your hearts are fatte as Brawne, stony as flint, impenitrable as Adamant: therfore many woords needes not, or at least boote not: yet some will I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowe, either to note your folly, or giue others war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by your fault.</p>
            <p>The roote of all euil is idlenes, and idlenes is your only excercise, except vnlawfull gaming, an excercise woorsse (if woorsse may be) than idlenes it selfe. For besides the damnable blasphemy among you vsed, beggery and want howerly awayteth yee, which you through impatience cannot bear, but following <hi>Iobs</hi> wiues wicked counsaile, cursse God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by seeking others destruction, hasten your owne dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes. Of you there are two sortes, neither tollerable, but one especially intollerable: The moste to be fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of two bad, are those whose parents (by too much cockring) hindred their youth from any honest im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, and now in age they thinke it shame to learne. But the other [vylest of all vyle people] are
<pb facs="tcp:176907:10"/> those that haue handy-crafts or other meanes to liue and yet dayly follow dicing houses, while their care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wiues, weeping children, and hunger-bitten fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milyes, suffer heart sorrow for their lost time and loose expence. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calleth such, infidels, how the Heathen haue punished such, many storyes testifye: Lord roote them from this Citie and Suburbs, and put in the Magistrates heads to punish them with more and more seueritie: For these and their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions are causes of all mutinies: and it is miraculous they haue not long since wrought some great mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, such a malcontent was <hi>Grant,</hi> by loose life gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen to pouertie: and to raise his state, what course takes he, but to be a ring-leader of rebellion, and to intice yong men and Prentises to his faction. Well God hath cut him off, and will vndoutedly cut you all off that intend so ill: therfore in a woord I intreat yee, that haue no sciences to liue by, serue honorably for your Prince and Country, and dye not infamou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sly among your familiars. To the other I will vse no intreatie, for that which wife and childrens teares cannot obtaine, onely authority must compell. Which God strengthen, for the conuersation or confusion of the euill.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:176907:11"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176907:11"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176907:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>